Jack: The Importance of
the different stages of the
software development lifecycle.
So, let’s review these stages and look
at their importance in more detail.
The initial stages of requirement,
gather, and analysis are the key planning
stages where the requirements need
to be fully understood so as to know
what the client’s requirements are.
These can be analysed in order to build
a strong foundation for the product.
Leah: Careful analysis of the client’s
needs is necessary to make sure
that all requirements will be met.
Misunderstandings at this stage could
result in wasted work and could be
costly so it is essential that the IT
team, often the Business Analyst and
the Project Manager, set up a meeting
with the client to gather all the
information like what they want to
build, who will be the end-user and
what is the purpose of the product.
For example, if the client needs
an application involving financial
transactions, they need to know what
these would involve, how they would be
done such as in what currencies etc.
Jack: Once the requirements are clearly
understood, the SRS [Software Requirement
Specification] document is created, and
any analysis is carried out to check the
development achievability of the product.
The analysis breaks the project
down into clearly defined tasks and
outlines the responsibilities of
each department at each stage through
to the delivery of the product.
It will also focus on time frames
and costing associated with
the development of the product.
Leah: The next design stage
involves designing the system
architecture that will be used for
implementing the system development.
This phase will detail, the
necessary specifications, features
and operations that will satisfy
the functional requirements of
the proposed software product.
End users and software engineering
professionals will consider the essential
components [hardware and/or software]
structure [networking capabilities],
processing and procedures for the
system to accomplish its objectives.
At this stage the external design may
also be considered, and any mock-ups made.
Jack: Once all the planning and design
stages are completed the development
or implementation stage begins.
Developers will start coding carefully
following any software requirements and
specifications in the SRS document as
well as internal design instructions.
All the components of the software
are implemented in this stage and if
the guidelines have all been followed
this should proceed without problems.
Most of the time actions may
involve writing totally new code
and developing a totally new system.
But sometimes actions may involve moving
data and components from an old system
and placing them in the new system.
Any developments done to an existing
system will need to be done out of peak
business hours to minimise disruptions.
Leah: The ‘testing’ phase always starts
when the coding is completed, and the
product modules are released for testing.
In this phase, the developed software
is tested thoroughly, and any
defects or bugs found are assigned
to developers to get them fixed.
Test engineers will perform various types
of functional and non-functional testing
related to core applications, text input,
security and scalability issues if needed.
Retesting is also done until
the point at which the software
meets the client’s expectations.
Testers will refer to the SRS document
to make sure that the software
is as per the client’s standard.
Jack: Once the testing is over
and the software demonstrated to
be ‘working’ it can be deployed
in the business environment.
However, User Acceptance Testing
[UAT] may need to be carried out
first before final deployment in a
replica of the intended environment.
The client along with the developers
can test the system before it
is signed off and goes ‘live’
Leah: Even after deployment as the
client uses the software issues may arise
or enhancements may need to be made.
The software developers will be
responsible for maintaining the system.
They will also be called upon to
produce updates and monitor any
issues that may arise in the future.
Jack: The software development life cycle
approach to creating software can be a
time-consuming process, but if it is done
correctly, it should run quite smoothly.
Some steps are more difficult than others
but should not be rushed or overlooked,
as an oversight can prevent an entire
system from functioning properly.
Understanding the different stages of
the process is important and essential
to successful planning, design, and
implementation of all software systems.